
<!--
/*
===========================================================================
             Software Engineering Ethics Debater (SWED) Argument Schemes
				  Copyright (C) 2019 Nancy Green
							
These are sample argument schemes for use with SWED software in an AI
Ethics course.

Software Engineering Ethics Debater (SWED) is free software: you can redistribute it and/or 
modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by
the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License, or
(at your option) any later version.

SWED Source Code is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
GNU General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with SWED Source Code.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.

If you have questions concerning this license or the applicable additional 
terms, you may contact Dr. Nancy Green at the University of North
Carolina at Greensboro.			
===========================================================================
*/
-->
<schemeList>
    <argScheme>
        <title>Defense by Cyberweapon</title>
        <premises>
			<premise>
				<name>Just cause</name>
				<definition>Describe the reason for using the cyberweapon in terms of self-defense or defense of others.</definition>
			</premise>
			<premise>
				<name>Last resort</name>
				<definition>Describe how no other actions are available in this case.</definition>
			</premise>
			<premise>
				<name>Ethical criteria</name>
				<definition>Give the ethical criteria justifying use of the cyberweapon in this case.</definition>
			</premise>
        </premises>
        <conclusion>It is acceptable to some degree to deploy the cyberweapon against the adversary.</conclusion>
        <CQs>
			<CQ>Proportionality: Is the harm to the adversary from the cyberweapon proportional to the harm inflicted by the adversary?</CQ>
			<CQ>Legitimate target: Is the target of the cyberweapon the actual source of harm?</CQ>
			<CQ>Right intention: Is there an ulterior motive such as commercial gain for using the cyberweapon?</CQ>
			<CQ>Intrinsically evil: Is use of the cyberweapon inhumane or horrific?</CQ>
            <CQ>Trust/Transparency: Are the reasons for the cyberweapon’s actions clear?</CQ>
            <CQ>Control: If the cyberweapon’s actions do not serve the user's goals, can the user intervene to modify its actions or abort its mission?</CQ>
			<CQ>Reliability:  Is the cyberweapon likely to function as intended under expected conditions of use?</CQ>
			<CQ>Exceptional conditions: Is the cyberweapon being used under conditions for which it was not designed? </CQ>
			<CQ>Accountability: Is there a governmental or private organization that can be held accountable for the cyberweapon’s actions?</CQ>
        </CQs>
    </argScheme>
    <argScheme>
        <title>Accept Negative Consequences</title>
        <premises>
            <premise>
				<name>Negative consequences</name>
				<definition>Give the likely negative consequences of the action.</definition>
			</premise>
            <premise>
				<name>Ethical criteria</name>
				<definition>Give the ethical criteria for the acceptability of the action in spite of the negative consequences.</definition>
			</premise>
			<premise>
				<name>Mitigating Factor</name>
				<definition>Explain why the degree or risk of harm from these consequences is within acceptable limits.</definition>
			</premise>
        </premises>
        <conclusion>The action is acceptable to some degree.</conclusion>
        <CQs>
			<CQ>Risk: Is the risk of these negative consequences unacceptably high?</CQ>
			<CQ>Degree of harm:  Is the degree of harm from these negative consequences unacceptably high?</CQ>
        </CQs>
    </argScheme>
    <argScheme>
        <title>Reject Negative Consequences</title>
        <premises>
            <premise>
				<name>Negative consequences</name>
				<definition>Give the likely negative consequences of the action.</definition>
			</premise>
			<premise>
				<name>Ethical criteria</name>
				<definition>Give the ethical criteria for the non-acceptability of the action due to the negative consequences.</definition>
			</premise>
			<premise>
				<name>Non-acceptability Factor</name>
				<definition>Explain why the degree or risk of harm from these consequences is not within acceptable limits.</definition>
			</premise>
        </premises>
        <conclusion>The action is not acceptable to some degree.</conclusion>
        <CQs>
			<CQ>Risk: Is the risk of these negative consequences acceptably low?</CQ>
			<CQ>Degree of harm:  Is the degree of harm from these negative consequences acceptably low?</CQ>
        </CQs>
    </argScheme>
    </schemeList>
